<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>New Projects on TinyPlant: Ian Breckheimer&#39;s Spatial Ecology and Global Change Laboratory</title>
    <link>https://tinyplant.org/categories/new-projects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in New Projects on TinyPlant: Ian Breckheimer&#39;s Spatial Ecology and Global Change Laboratory</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 10:23:27 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://tinyplant.org/categories/new-projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Drone Workshop 2018</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/post/2018-08-01-drone-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 10:23:27 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/post/2018-08-01-drone-workshop/</guid>
      <description>In June I led a half-day workshop on using drone imagery in field research at Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory. The workshop was a ton of fun (I miss teaching!), and I decided to share the workshop materials here.
Preparation Here&amp;rsquo;s what you need to take full advantage of the workshop materials:
A computer: A big part of the workshop is focused on transforming the imagery we get from drones into scientifically valid data, so you will need to bring a computer with you when you come so you can participate in the hands-on steps of the processing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecology by Drone</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/post/2018-06-01-drone-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 10:23:27 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/post/2018-06-01-drone-ecology/</guid>
      <description>This summer I&amp;rsquo;m starting a new project that aims to measure flowering phenology in a new and exciting way: extracting flower counts using deep learning from high-resolution aerial imagery collected with a small UAV. This has brought me to Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory in Gothic Colorado, which is home to one of North America&amp;rsquo;s longest-running phenology monitoring programs.
The inspiration This project has been bouncing around in my head for a while: how can we see and understand the landscape like a pollinator does?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>