<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>TinyPlant: Ian Breckheimer&#39;s Spatial Ecology and Global Change Laboratory on TinyPlant: Ian Breckheimer&#39;s Spatial Ecology and Global Change Laboratory</title>
    <link>https://tinyplant.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content in TinyPlant: Ian Breckheimer&#39;s Spatial Ecology and Global Change Laboratory on TinyPlant: Ian Breckheimer&#39;s Spatial Ecology and Global Change Laboratory</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Herbarium Phenology</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/project/herbarium-pheno/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/project/herbarium-pheno/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Millions of herbarium specimens collected over the past two centuries provide unique insights into continental-scale patterns of plant diversity. With my colleagues Daniel Park, Aaron Ellison, and Charles Davis at Harvard University, we have developed an approach to crowd-source reproductive phenology data collection from digitized specimens. Our initial work resulted in recording buds, flowers, and fruits from ~10,000 specimens of 30 plant species. We have used the data to estimate continental-scale patterns of plant reproductive phenology, revealing a surprising amount of variation in plant responses to climate across regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A paper describing this work is currently in press at ProcB.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecology by Drone</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/post/2018-06-01-drone-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 10:23:27 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/post/2018-06-01-drone-ecology/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This summer I&amp;rsquo;m starting a new project that aims to measure flowering phenology in a new and exciting way: extracting flower counts using deep learning from high-resolution aerial imagery collected with a small UAV. This has brought me to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rmbl.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; in Gothic Colorado, which is home to one of North America&amp;rsquo;s longest-running phenology monitoring programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-inspiration&#34;&gt;The inspiration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project has been bouncing around in my head for a while: how can we see and understand the landscape like a pollinator does? The main obstacle is a mismatch between the spatial scales of the processes that we are interested in (pollinator foraging over large landscapes), and the data that we can actually collect (floral abundance and pollinator visitation in tiny plots or transects). If we could develop a way to monitor the timing and abundance of flowering efficiently over large extents, though, we might be able to piece together how the landscapes of floral resources for pollinators change over the course of the season, or even how longer-term trends like climate change are likely to alter these spatial patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-barriers&#34;&gt;The barriers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the development of modern quadcopter drones with high-resolution cameras, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t feasible to collect imagery data at a high enough resolution to see individual flowers at a large enough extent to say anything about landscape patterns. Essentially flowers are extremely small (2mm - 5cm), and the landscape is extremely large. Even with a 12 megapixel camera (standard on consumer drones until recently) we would have to fly extremely slowly at 5m above the ground to capture imagery with high enough ground resolution (3mm) to see most flowers. Luckily, over the past few years the technology has finally matured enough to make this more feasible: A drone with a 20 megapixel camera can fly at 10m and still capture 3mm imagery mosaics. Flight times of up to 30 minutes gives each flight a survey area of about 1 hectare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with good imagery, counting flowers by hand wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be feasible over large areas because there can be many tens of thousands of flowers in a hectare of meadow. This is where machine learning comes in. Flowers (or inflorescences) are discrete, compact  objects with contrasting colors againsta soil or vegetation background. These objects are great candidates for being accurately counted using new computer vision tools called convolutional neural networks. I plan to use frameworks developed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.planet.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Planet Labs&lt;/a&gt; and others to automate this classification task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ground-truthing&#34;&gt;Ground-truthing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drones provide a great top-down view of ecosystems, but they can&amp;rsquo;t see through dense vegetation. How well can photo-based counts of flowers align with more traditional plot-based data? This is what has brought me to Colorado, where researchers have been collecting field data on wilflower phenology in a network of 30 plots since 1973! I&amp;rsquo;m coordinating with the project field lead Jane Ogilvie to make sure my drone imagery lines up with the timing of their field surveys. How well can we do? Time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wish-me-luck&#34;&gt;Wish me luck!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;https://tinyplant.org/img/drone-ir-selfie.gif&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;False color images from the IR camera that I use to measure plant greenness.&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BloomFinder</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/project/bloomfinder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/project/bloomfinder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For decades, scientists have used the seasonal timing of events like flowering to track the impacts of climate change. As these impacts accelerate, it’s becoming more and more important to understand where changes in climate are having the most severe impacts on ecosystems. Tracking flowering can help us understand how climate change is altering the risks of extreme climate events like growing season frost and drought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, new machine-learning approaches (“deep learning”) have finally made it possible to trawl the web for observations of specific species in specific places. This is a new type of observing system that is sometimes called a “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wordnik.com/words/macroscope&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;macroscope&lt;/a&gt;” because it allows us to see patterns at extremely large scales, patterns that would otherwise be invisible. Over the next two years, we will be developing this system and using it to track bloom timing across mountain ecosystems in the western USA.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Landscapes of Flowering</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/project/flower-landscapes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/project/flower-landscapes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Species interactions, like the critical links between plants and their animal pollinators, play out over space and through time. Despite their inherently spatial nature, much of the scientific work on these links, and how environmental changes like climate change might affect them, treats the landscape as homogeneous. We are currently working on two projects that try to understand how plant flowering is distributed across landscapes. With my collaborator &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/ellijtheobald/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Elli Theobald&lt;/a&gt;, we are reconstructing the landscapes of flowering for subalpine meadows in Mt. Rainier National Park, using data from low snowpack &amp;ldquo;snow drought&amp;rdquo; years to help us understand the impacts of climate change on flowering synchrony and pollen dispersal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018 we started using drones to collect ultra-high resolution aerial imagery of meadows near &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rmbl.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; in southwestern Colorado. We are currently training a machine learning system to automatically identify and count these flowers in imagery data. We will combine these counts with information about the nectar and pollen resources that each flower provides to reconstruct the landscape of floral resources for pollinators at the same sites where &lt;a href=&#34;https://irwinlab.weebly.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Becky Irwin&amp;rsquo;s lab&lt;/a&gt; at NC State University monitors populations of bumblebees and other pollinators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Microclimates</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/project/microclimate-mapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/project/microclimate-mapping/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Fine-scale patterns in climate drive huge changes in the composition and function of ecosystems, but are poorly represented in models that we use to anticipate climate change impacts. I&amp;rsquo;m using measurements from a large network of microclimate sensors, remote-sensing, and weather station data to explore how different aspects of climate vary across the steep topographic gradients of Mt. Rainier National Park. Myself and my collaborators &lt;a href=&#34;https://faculty.washington.edu/jhrl/Index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Janneke Hille Ris Lambers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://depts.washington.edu/mtnhydr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jessica Lundquist&lt;/a&gt; want to understand which parts of the landscape are the least strongly coupled to the regional climate system. These sites are potential microclimate &amp;ldquo;refugia&amp;rdquo; that could help species adapt to a changing climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of our preliminary data products are available through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://tinyplant.org/blog/2016/07/22/MORAclim-intro/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MORAClim&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phenological Reassembly</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/project/pheno-reassembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/project/pheno-reassembly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Climate change is altering ecological communities by changing species distributions and abundances. This &amp;ldquo;community reassembly&amp;rdquo; has profound consequences for species interactions and ecosystem function. Communities can also reassemble in time if their seasonal periods of activity respond differently to climate cues. We developed this concept, called &amp;ldquo;phenological reassembly&amp;rdquo; by examining how co-flowering relationships changed in a diverse perennial plant community in Mt. Rainier National Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project resulted in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/ecy.1996&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; published in Ecology in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ranges and Disturbance</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/project/range-disturbance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/project/range-disturbance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Long-term studies which measure changes in species distributions with climate change have revealed a surprising diversity of responses. Although a majority of species distributions are tracking climates shifting upslope and higher in latitude, the ranges of many species have failed to closely track climate, and range limits of some species have moved downhill or south, counter to the expected direction. The dominant factors driving these “counter-gradient” range shifts are unclear, but many have suggested that they reflect the imprint of ecological interactions, novel physiological responses, or past biogeographical events in defining contemporary range limits. Here we suggest that climate’s influence on disturbance regimes and metapopulation dynamics — broad scale patterns of colonization and persistence across networks of habitat patches — play an under-appreciated role in determining the response of species ranges to climate change, and may explain some of the diversity of climate-driven range-shifts observed in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this case, we marshaled evidence from a field study of two ecologically similar riparian plant species (common yellow monkeyflower, Erythranthe guttata, and mountain monkeyflower, E. caespitosa) in Mt. Rainier National Park, WA, USA. We combined detailed demographic data collected from individuals growing in experimental populations across the range limits of both species with four years of comprehensive census data from wild populations. We then used this data to parameterize a spatial population model that incorporates the effects of climate and other habitat attributes on local demographic performance, as well as on colonization and local extinction processes. Simulating range dynamics at Mt. Rainier under a variety of climate change and disturbance scenarios, we found that both the magnitude and direction of predicted elevation range shifts differed dramatically between species and were extremely sensitive to changes in the disturbance regime. Increases in flood disturbance, predicted in the region by the late 21st century, caused the upper range limit of E. guttata, the low-elevation species, to move up in elevation twice as far as in a scenario assuming no change to the disturbance regime. Under current levels of flood disturbance, or if disturbance becomes less frequent, models projected downhill shifts in the low-elevation limit of E. caespitosa in scenarios assuming considerable warming. Overall, simulated range shifts were considerably more sensitive to climate impacts on colonization and disturbance processes than impacts on local demography for both species, indicating that neglecting these important processes might lead to misleading predictions about range shifts in response to changes in climate. Our results highlight the importance of interactions between climate, local demography, disturbance, and colonization processes in determining the response of species ranges to environmental change. We suspect that these interactions are important in many systems where populations are patchy near range limits, and that understanding their role will bolster efforts to forecast the impacts of climate change on species distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social-ecological Mismatch</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/project/visitor-phenology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/project/visitor-phenology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As climate change accelerates, it is critical for scientists and policymakers to understand how climate influences the links between ecosystems and their social context. Surprisingly, despite increased attention to coupled analyses of social-ecological systems, there have been few studies that simultaneously measure how changes in climate drive changes in the temporal distribution of natural resources and the people that use those resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We measured how climate influences the spatial and temporal match between human visitors and seasonal displays of subalpine wildflowers at Mt. Rainier National Park, where wildflower blooms are a key visitor draw. We use a large, field-validated dataset derived from the Flickr photo sharing service and volunteer citizen scientists to show that the phenological match between these ecological and social systems is sensitive to the date that seasonal snowpack disappears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early snow melts, comparable to conditions predicted in the late 21st century, cause reduced temporal overlap between wildflowers and park visitors (by 17.4 to 48.9 %). In-line with ecological and social theory, we expect social-ecological mismatches in phenology to be common in systems where users of natural resources (i.e. park visitors) have imperfect information about climatic drivers of their resource, and where seasonal shifts in their behavior is constrained by non-climatic factors. Recent dramatic growth in the volume of georeferenced citizen observations coupled with recent advances in machine learning, will soon make it feasible to test these hypotheses at very large spatial scales.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The spatial scaling of flowering phenology: How much could landscape heterogeneity buffer mountain meadow plants and pollinators from phenological mismatch?</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/talk/mtnclim-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/talk/mtnclim-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Launching the BloomFinder Project</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/post/2017-12-01-bloomfinder/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 10:23:27 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/post/2017-12-01-bloomfinder/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;rsquo;m excited to officially launch &lt;a href=&#34;https://bloomfinder.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BloomFinder&lt;/a&gt;, a new citizen-science project aimed at tracking the blooms of wildflowers using photographs on social media platforms like Flickr and Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-bloomfinder&#34;&gt;Why BloomFinder?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For decades, scientists have used the seasonal timing of events like flowering to track the impacts of climate change. As these impacts accelerate, it&amp;rsquo;s becoming more and more important to understand where changes in climate are having the most severe impacts on ecosystems. Tracking flowering can help us understand how climate change is altering the risks of extreme climate events like growing season frost and drought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-are-we-doing-this&#34;&gt;How are we doing this?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, new machine-learning approaches (&amp;ldquo;deep learning&amp;rdquo;) have finally made it possible to trawl the web for observations of specific species in specific places. This is a new type of observing system that is sometimes called a &amp;ldquo;macroscope&amp;rdquo; because it allows us to see patterns at extremely large scales, patterns that would otherwise be invisible. Over the next two years, we will be developing this system and using it to track bloom timing across mountain ecosystems in the western USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-else-is-cool-about-bloomfinder&#34;&gt;What else is cool about BloomFinder?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to advancing our scientific understanding, BloomFinder will also generate some great information for wildflower buffs that just want to catch ecosystems in peak bloom. In the course of the project, we will be creating detailed maps of the abundance of our focal species, and will eventually be able to post real-time forecasts of bloom timing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-i-help&#34;&gt;How can I help?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early 2018, we will start recruiting a small army of volunteers to help us train computers to recognize wildflowers. We are still working out the details here, but we will likely use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Zooniverse&lt;/a&gt; platform, which makes it easy and fun to classify photographs. If you&amp;rsquo;d rather donate your money than your time, we would love to get contributions via our project page on &lt;a href=&#34;https://experiment.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;experiment.com&lt;/a&gt;. Regardless, you can help spread the word about BloomFinder by liking our page on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/BloomFinder&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; and following us on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BloomFinder&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ian has moved to Harvard OEB</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/post/2017-10-01-harvard/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/post/2017-10-01-harvard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As of November 2017, I&amp;rsquo;ll be officially starting my new NSF-supported postdoctoral fellowship in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://oeb.harvard.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Department of Organismic and Evolutionary Biology &lt;/a&gt; at Harvard University. I&amp;rsquo;ll be based out of &lt;a href=&#34;https://huh.harvard.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Harvard University Herbaria&lt;/a&gt;, where I&amp;rsquo;ll be associated with the lab of &lt;a href=&#34;https://davislab.oeb.harvard.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Charles C. Davis&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve been in the lab unofficially for almost a year, but it&amp;rsquo;s nice to finally be official!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate drives phenological reassembly of a mountain wildflower meadow community</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/publication/rainier-pheno-reassembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/publication/rainier-pheno-reassembly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More detail can easily be written here using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An evaluation of terrain‐based downscaling of fractional snow covered area data sets based on LiDAR‐derived snow data and orthoimagery</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/publication/snow-downscaling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/publication/snow-downscaling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2017 MORA Snow Melt Forecasts</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/post/2017-06-01-snowmelt-forecasts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/post/2017-06-01-snowmelt-forecasts/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve updated my seasonal snow melt forecasts for Mt. Rainier National Park to reflect the latest snow conditions in 2017. I&amp;rsquo;ll update these maps approximately every two weeks through the early summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The link to the most up-to-date forecast map is &lt;a href=&#34;https://ibreckhe.github.io/snow_forecasts.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If you zoom in on the map enough, you should see overlayed data for roads and trails!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of June 21st, 2017, I&amp;rsquo;m making the following projections for snow melt timing for key parts of Mt. Rainier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meadows around Reflection Lakes:&lt;/strong&gt; July 1st - July 10th&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paradise Park above Jackson Visitor Center:&lt;/strong&gt; July 20th - August 1st&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yakima Park around Sunrise Visitor Center:&lt;/strong&gt; July 10th - July 20th&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower Spray Park above Mowich Lake Camp:&lt;/strong&gt; July 15th - July 25th&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meadows near Tipsoo Lake (Chinook Pass)&lt;/strong&gt; July 5th - July 15th&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tinyplant.org/pages/snow_forecasts.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img width=800 src=&#34;https://tinyplant.org/img/forecast_6_7_17.png&#34; alt=&#34;Snow Forecast Example&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-is-this-forecast-generated&#34;&gt;How is this forecast generated?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This forecast is a statistical estimate based on three key types of information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. Historical SNOTEL Data.&lt;/em&gt; The baseline data that informs this forecast is the relationship between the current size of the snowpack, and the date that snow eventually melted at the Paradise SNOTEL station during the 30 years of record. Snowpack melts later in years when more snow accumulates, so we can use that relationship to forecast the eventual date of melt at Paradise as long as we know how large the snowpack currently is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2. Microclimate Sensors.&lt;/em&gt; To extrapolate this forecast spatially, we use the relationship between when snow melted at the Paradise SNOTEL station and when it melted at a network of ~400 snow duration sensors distributed throughout the park during the previous 6 years. These sensors allow us to estimate how much topography, canopy cover, and geographic position affect when snow melts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3. Expert knowledge.&lt;/em&gt; The relationship between SNOTEL station melt dates and melt dates in other parts of the park varies from year to year, depending on the wind direction during winter storms and the average snow level during those storms. We use reports of snow from NPS crews, Washington DOT road closure reports, and information from other SNOTEL stations to select from the recent historical record the year where these patterns of snow accumulation most resemble the current year, and base our spatial forecasts on the spatial pattern of melt that most closely resembles the current year. We also adjust the forecast melt rates based on NOAA seasonal climate outlooks. If the outlook is for a warmer-than-average spring, then the forecast melt date is adjusted forward up to 10 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-much-uncertainty-is-there-in-the-forecast&#34;&gt;How much uncertainty is there in the forecast?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That depends on when and where. The uncertainty is generally high early in the season, and decreases as the spring melt season progresses. Early-season forecasts have an average uncertainty (80% prediction interval) of plus-or-minus approximately 3 weeks, and that decreases to approximately plus-or-minus one week as snowpack at the Paradie SNOTEL station reaches 25% of it&amp;rsquo;s peak seasonal value. Uncertainty is also high in parts of Mt. Rainier National Park where we have few measurements, including remote areas and high elevations (above 7000&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-up-with-that-mid-elevation-snow&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s up with that mid-elevation snow?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The early-season forecasts sometimes predict snow at mid-elevations (3000 - 4500ft) when there is no snowpack on the ground. This is because these elevations still are at risk of a late-spring snowstorm, and the forecast is for the last date of snow cover, not the melt date of persistent snowpack. At higher elevations at Mt. Rainier (above 4500ft) these two things are usually the same, but they differ at lower elevations where snow is not as persistant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-put-this-forecast-together&#34;&gt;Who put this forecast together?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forecast was created by Ian Breckheimer and Janneke Hille Ris Lambers at the University of Washington, based on initial work done by Kevin Ford, now at the USDA Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station. Groundwork for the forecast was funded by NASA and in-kind support from the NW Climate Science Center and the National Park Service.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
