<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Landscape on TinyPlant: Ian Breckheimer&#39;s Spatial Ecology and Global Change Laboratory</title>
    <link>https://tinyplant.org/tags/landscape/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Landscape on TinyPlant: Ian Breckheimer&#39;s Spatial Ecology and Global Change Laboratory</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://tinyplant.org/tags/landscape/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Landscapes of Flowering</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/project/flower-landscapes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/project/flower-landscapes/</guid>
      <description>Species interactions, like the critical links between plants and their animal pollinators, play out over space and through time. Despite their inherently spatial nature, much of the scientific work on these links, and how environmental changes like climate change might affect them, treats the landscape as homogeneous. We are currently working on two projects that try to understand how plant flowering is distributed across landscapes. With my collaborator Elli Theobald, we are reconstructing the landscapes of flowering for subalpine meadows in Mt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Microclimates</title>
      <link>https://tinyplant.org/project/microclimate-mapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tinyplant.org/project/microclimate-mapping/</guid>
      <description>Fine-scale patterns in climate drive huge changes in the composition and function of ecosystems, but are poorly represented in models that we use to anticipate climate change impacts. I&amp;rsquo;m using measurements from a large network of microclimate sensors, remote-sensing, and weather station data to explore how different aspects of climate vary across the steep topographic gradients of Mt. Rainier National Park. Myself and my collaborators Janneke Hille Ris Lambers and Jessica Lundquist want to understand which parts of the landscape are the least strongly coupled to the regional climate system.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>